Joseph F. Niedermayer Papers VHP2006/5
CCSU Veterans History Project
Joseph F. Niedermayer Papers
Bulk, 1971-1975
1971 - 1975, 2006
VHP2006/5
CCSU Veterans History Project
263.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details Joesph Niedemayer's experience serving in Vietnam War in weapon department of USS Enterprise(CVN-65). The collection contains video oral history interview, personal and military documents, and photographs.
Niedemayer, Joseph F., (Joseph Frank), 1952 -
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Niedermayer enlisted in the United States Navy in October of 1971. He did his basic training at the Great Lakes Naval training center in Illinois. After graduation from basic training, Niedermayer had 24 hours before he was to report to his duty station in Alameda, Ca. He was assigned to the U.S.S. Enterprise, which was a nuclear aircraft carrier assigned to the South China Sea, where its purpose was to patrol the waters around Vietnam, and was sometimes engaged in naval combat. Niedermayer's job on the ship was in the weapons division, which actually operated seven decks below the main deck. He was discharged from the navy in October of 1975. He returned to Connecticut and used the G.I. Bill to continue his education. Shortly after returning home he began a career with the Connecticut Department of Public Safety, where he still works to the date of the interview. He also joined the VFW, and has been able to attend a reunion of the U.S.S. Enterprise.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Enterprise (Aircraft carrier: CVA(N) 65).; United States. Navy.; Alameda (Calif.); Great Lakes Naval Training Center (Great Lakes, Ill.); Mauritius; Nuclear aircraft carriers; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii); South China Sea; Subic Bay (Philippines); Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narrative, American; Vietnam War, 1961-1975--Naval operations, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2006/5.I
  - Joseph Niedemayer military identification Card, Nov. 16, 1977; VHP2006/5.I.1
  - U.S.S. Enterprise CVAN-65 Crew Member card, n.d.; VHP2006/5.I.2
  - USS enterprise Ordinance Elevator Operator’s Card, Sep. 17, 1972; VHP2006/05.I.3
  - USN Aviation Support Equipment Operator’s Identification Card, 1972; VHP2006/05.I.4
  - Postcard Joseph sent to his parent from Hawaii, Oct. 2 1972; VHP2006/05.I.5; 2.0 Digital objects
  - USN Recruiting Service Landlubber (Shellback certificate), Oct. 28 1971; VHP2006/05.I.6
  - Discharge certificate (form DD - 214N), Nov. 11 1975; VHP2006/05.I.7
  - Postcard Joseph sent to his parent from Hong Kong, Nov. 7, 1974; VHP2006/05.I.8; 2.0 Digital objects
  - General Mess Meal Pass, 1970s; VHP2006/05.I.9
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States member card, 2000s; VHP2006/05.I.10
  - Service stripe, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.11
  - Shoulder Patch, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.12
  - USS Enterprise Uniform Shoulder Patch, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.13
  - USS Enterprise CVAN-65 Patch, 1970s; VHP2006/05.I.14
  - U.S.S. Enterprise CVAN/CVN-65 Association card, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.15
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars card, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.16
  - Shellback card, n.d.; VHP2006/05.I.17
  - Interview synopsis, Jul. 24, 2009; VHP2006/05.I.18
- Series II: Publications, VHP2006/5.II
  - The Big E (Vol XIV: No.3), May 1975; VHP2006/05.II.1; 13.0 Digital objects
  - Serving the Nation: USS Enterprise (CVAN-65), Westpac 1972-73 (Book), circa 1972; VHP2006/05.II.2; 168.0 Digital objects
  - “Welcome Aboard the Big E” booklet, 1974; VHP2006/5.II.3; 13.0 Digital objects
  - U.S.S. Enterprise CVAN 65 Ledger about Crossing the line ceremonies, Jan. 16, 1975; VHP2006/5.II.3; 3.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2006/5.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2006/5.III
    - Joseph Niedermayer on U.S.S. Enterprise's flight deck, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.1
    - U.S.S. Enterprise in port, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.2
    - “island structure” (command center tower) on board U.S.S. Enterprise, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.3
    - Base of USS Enterprise “island structure”, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.4
      General note
      The #65 is emblazoned in lights
    - The “island” and planes on U.S.S. Enterprise, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.5
    - Grumman EA-6B Prowler, electronic warfare aircraft, and Grumman E-2 Hawkeye, tactical Airborne Early Warning (AEW) aircraft on board USS Enterprise. South China Sea - Vietnam., 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.6
    - McDonnell Douglas F-4 Phantom II on board USS Enterprise. South China Sea - Vietnam., 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.7
    - North American A-5 (RA-5C) Vigilante, a reconnaissance variants. (2nd plane from front) USS Enterprise, South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.8
    - Aircrafts on USS Enterprise, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.9
    - A-7E Corsair II fighter/bomber on USS Enterprise flight deck. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.10
    - Grumman A-6B Intruder board USS Enterprise. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.11
    - Sikorsky SH-3 "Sea King" helicopter landing on USS Enterprise. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.12
    - F-4 Phantom being towed to catapult to launch, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.13
    - F-4 Phantom on board USS Enterprise, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.14
    - F-4 Phantom on board USS Enterprise, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.15
    - F-4 Phantom getting ready to launch, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.16
    - F-4 Phantom (back) and A-5 Vigilante (front) being launched simultaneously, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.17
    - American planes returning to USS Enterprise at night, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.18
    - USS Enterprise coming along side refueling ship. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.19
    - Front end of refueling ship. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.20
    - Refueling ship. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.21
      Refueling ship also brought the USS Enterprise food, bombs, etc
    - Refueling ship ,refueling lines can be seen in back. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.22
    - Pallet of bombs being high-lined to USS Enterprise from refueling ship. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.23
    - Supplies being "VERTREP" (Vertical replenishment,a method of supply of seaborne vessels by helicopter.), 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.24
    - Supplies being "VERTREP" (Vertical replenishment,a method of supply of seaborne vessels by helicopter.), 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.25
    - Joseph Niedermayer with 20mm anti aircraft gun on USS Enterprise. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.26
    - Joseph Niedermayer with 20mm anti aircraft gun. South China Sea - Vietnam, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.27
    - Joseph Niedermayer and Timothy Hollingsworth (back), on liberty - Hong Kong, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.28
    - Joseph Niedermayer, Michael Harrison Smith (Right) waring new leather jackets while on liberty. Hong Kong, 1972 - 1973; VHP2006/5.III.29
      Liberty: A pass for up to 4 days’ R&R (Rest & Recreation)
    - Joseph Niedermayer sitting in the shop, with work chart in the background., Jun. 7, 1947; VHP2006/5.III.30
    - Joseph Niedermayer, West Pacific., Oct. 9, 1947; VHP2006/5.III.31
    - Joseph Niedermayer at work, n.d.; VHP2006/5.III.32
    - Joseph Niedermayer’s medals, 1970s; VHP2006/5.III.33
    - Joseph Niedermayer at his resident, July 2009; VHP2006/5.III.34
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2006/5.IIIb
    - Oral history interview, Jul. 24, 2009; VHP2006/5.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2006/5, Bin VHP Interview 2006)